Cross Creek 101

A Hands-On Training Syllabus for the Cross Creek ICS/OT Security Range

By Britley Hoff

2026 Edition

In November 2023 a water authority in Aliquippa, Pennsylvania lost control of a booster station. Not to a zero-day, not to a nation-state exploit chain. To a programmable logic controller sitting on the public internet with the password still set to the number one, four times. A group calling itself CyberAv3ngers walked in the front door and put a message on the screen, and they did the same thing to water systems in several other states. A few months later, in Lviv, malware called FrostyGoop spoke plain Modbus to a rack of heating controllers and left six hundred apartment buildings cold for two days in January.

None of that was clever. That is the part people miss. The controllers that run water plants and substations were designed in an era when "on the network" meant "on a serial cable in a locked room," and most of them still trust anything that can reach the port. The attacks that are working right now are the boring ones: default credentials, a protocol with no authentication, a flat network, an engineering laptop nobody segmented off.

I have spent a good part of my career on the other side of this. Alongside the mainframe work I am a Master-level industrial electrician, and I have wired, programmed, and troubleshot Siemens and Allen-Bradley PLCs and their ladder logic on the kind of equipment this course simulates. I have stood in the MCC room. I know what a metering pump sounds like when it is running wide open, and I know that "just restore from the golden program" is a sentence that assumes somebody kept a golden program.

This is a seven-session course built entirely on the Cross Creek range: a mock municipal water treatment plant and a small power substation, driven by three simulated controllers that speak the real protocols, Modbus/TCP, EtherNet/IP, and Siemens S7comm. A Python process simulator plays the physical world, coarsely and on purpose. Open a valve and the chlorine rises. Stop a pump and the tank drains. Every command in this book was run against the actual containers before it went to print.

The first four sessions are the attack half. You will find an internet-exposed HMI and log in with the factory account, stop the distribution pump with twenty lines of Python, drive the chlorine residual past four parts per million, halt a substation RTU, and replace a running control program with one that has the high-level interlock cut out. The last three are the defense half, run against the same range with one flag flipped: you segment the network, put a source allowlist on the controllers, lock the keyswitches, stand up an ICS-aware sensor, and rehearse the recovery. Then a capstone that chains the whole attack and then closes every hole, followed by an incident-response tabletop.

A training environment that is honest about its own edges is more useful than one that hopes you will not notice them. Where Cross Creek uses a stand-in, this book says so. The Allen-Bradley logic download, for instance, is not the real Studio 5000 wire format, because that cannot be reproduced without Rockwell's tooling; it is an unauthenticated service that swaps the controller's logic, and it teaches the concept and the detection, not the packet layout. That is called out where it happens.

Standing Up the Range

Cross Creek is one docker-compose stack. Ten containers on five bridge networks laid out along the Purdue model: an edge network for the attacker, an IT network, a DMZ, one flat OT network for the HMIs and PLCs, and an internal field bus. Every published port binds to 127.0.0.1. The attacker box has no route to the internet, and status.sh proves it.

cd crosscreek
./setup.sh              # preflight, build the images
./start.sh              # bring it up with the deliberate weaknesses on
./status.sh             # health, the loopback bind audit, the containment probe
./start.sh --segmented  # the defended topology, for Sessions 5 to 7
./reset.sh              # restore the golden state between cohorts

Surface | Address | Notes
Water HMI | http://127.0.0.1:8071 | the plant overview screen
Power HMI | http://127.0.0.1:8072 | the substation single-line
Water PLC runtime UI | http://127.0.0.1:8073 | OpenPLC-style console, used in Session 4
Water PLC (Modbus/TCP) | 127.0.0.1:5020 | container port 502
Dosing PLC (EtherNet/IP) | 127.0.0.1:4840 | container port 44818
Substation RTU (S7comm) | 127.0.0.1:1020 | container port 102
IDS alerts | http://127.0.0.1:9411 | segmented mode only

Accounts you are given

Who | Credentials | Use
Water and power HMI | admin / admin | the factory default the plant never changed
Water PLC runtime | openplc / openplc | the OpenPLC-style console, Session 4
Attacker workstation | docker exec -it crosscreek-attacker bash | scripts under /opt/scripts

The instructor edition of the scenario guide, docs/scenarios.md, maps every one of the ten planted weaknesses to the exact command that proves it, the physical consequence in the simulation, and the fix, with its CISA Cross-Sector Cybersecurity Performance Goal and its ISA/IEC 62443 clause. You work from docs/scenarios-trainee.md, the same document with the fix removed.

Authorised Use

Use Cross Creek only: on your own machine; in a lab you control; in a classroom or range where you have permission; under written rules of engagement for authorised training or assessment. Never point a Cross Creek command, script, payload, scan, or credential at a real utility, a real PLC, or any system you do not own. ICS attacks have physical consequences. People can be hurt. This range exists so you never have to learn that on a live one.

Session 1: Orientation and the Purdue Model

Goal for this session: get the range running, understand the ethics of what you are about to do, and map the plant by hand, the way an assessor maps a client site on day one. You will identify every zone, every controller, and every protocol before you send a single hostile packet. Do not try to exploit anything yet.

1.1 The Line You Do Not Cross

Web application testing has a forgiving failure mode. You knock a container over, you restart it, you file a finding. Industrial control systems do not work that way. The output of the logic you are poking is a pump, a valve, a breaker, a chemical feed. A stopped CPU can mean a tank overflows into a river. A tampered setpoint can mean the water leaving the plant is not safe to drink. A breaker operated at the wrong moment can drop power to a hospital.

So the rule for this course, and for the rest of your career, is simple. You run these techniques against equipment you own, or against a range built for the purpose, or against a client system under a signed rules-of-engagement document that a plant engineer has read and approved and is standing by to recover. Nothing else. Not "just a scan." Not "just reading, not writing," because on Modbus a read and a write are the same size and the same risk of confusing a device that has run for fifteen years without being spoken to by anything but its HMI.

Cross Creek exists so you can build the instinct without the consequences. Use it that way.

1.2 Bring the Range Up and Prove It Is Contained

Before anything sharper than a browser, prove to yourself the range cannot reach past your machine.

./setup.sh
./start.sh
./status.sh

status.sh checks three things: every published port is on 127.0.0.1, the attacker container has no working route to the internet, and nothing is bound where it should not be. It exits non-zero if any of that fails. Run it now, read the output, and get in the habit. On a real engagement, proving your test traffic stayed in scope is the same reflex, and you build it here.

1.3 The Purdue Model, and Where Cross Creek Sits In It

The Purdue Enterprise Reference Architecture, the "Purdue model," is how the ICS world talks about network layers. You do not need to recite it, but you need to recognise it, because every defense decision in Sessions 5 to 7 is an argument about which layer something belongs on.

Level | What lives there | Cross Creek
4 / 5 | enterprise IT, business systems | it-net 172.30.20.0/24
3.5 | the DMZ between IT and OT | dmz-net 172.30.30.0/24
3 | operations management, engineering workstations, historians | eng-ws, historian
2 | supervisory control, HMIs | hmi-water, hmi-power on ot-net
1 | controllers, PLCs, RTUs | plc-water, plc-dosing, plc-power on ot-net
0 | the physical process, sensors and actuators | process-sim on the internal sim-net

Notice that in the default range, Levels 1 and 2 share one flat network, ot-net. That is not a mistake in the lab. That is how a large number of real small utilities are actually built, and undoing it is the core of Session 5.

1.4 Map the Plant by Hand

Open both HMIs and behave like an operator. On the water side, http://127.0.0.1:8071, log in admin / admin and watch the plant run: the raw tank cycling between its setpoints as the intake pump duty-cycles, the chlorine residual holding at 2.5 ppm, the header pressure sitting near 60 psi. On the power side, http://127.0.0.1:8072, the bus at 50 Hz with all three breakers closed.

Now get on the attacker box and look at the network the way an intruder who just landed would.

docker exec -it crosscreek-attacker bash
ip route                                   # note: no default route, only the lab
python3 /opt/scripts/recon.py sweep        # TCP-connect scan of the OT /24

Write down, on paper, what answers and on what port:

172.30.40.10   8080/http            water HMI
172.30.40.11   8080/http            power HMI
172.30.40.20   502/modbus  8080/http   water PLC + its runtime console
172.30.40.21   44818/enip  8080/http   dosing controller + a logic-update service
172.30.40.22   102/s7comm          substation RTU
172.30.20.20   8080/http  5900/vnc  engineering workstation

Three industrial protocols, two web HMIs, an engineering box one hop away, and a service on the dosing controller that answers HTTP on 8080 and should make you curious. That is your attack surface, and you built the map, not a tool.

1.5 What You Should Notice

You are on a network that was never meant to have a hostile host on it, and it shows. Nothing asked you for a credential to run that scan. Every device answered. The protocols you found, Modbus, EtherNet/IP, S7comm, were all specified before authentication on a control network was considered a requirement, and none of the three will challenge you when you start issuing commands in the next session. The plant's entire security model, right now, is that the bad guys are not supposed to be able to get here. Sessions 2 through 4 are what happens when that assumption fails. Sessions 5 through 7 are how you build a real one.

Session 2: Exposure and Access

Goal for this session: get in the way the real intrusions of the last few years got in. No exploits, no memory corruption. A name server that tells you the whole plant, an exposed service, a default password, and an engineering workstation that hands you the keys. This is scenario 11, then scenarios 1 through 3.

2.1 Start With the Name

A real external assessment does not start with an IP address. It starts with a domain, and the first thing it asks is what the target's own name server will admit to. Cross Creek runs one, on the edge network, at 172.30.10.53, authoritative for crosscreek-water.lab and crosscreek-power.lab. In the flat topology it answers for the whole estate and it allows a zone transfer to anyone who asks.

python3 /opt/scripts/recon.py dns

That runs an AXFR against both zones and follows it with a reverse sweep of the OT segment. What comes back is the asset inventory, by function, with addresses:

plc-water.crosscreek-water.lab.    172.30.40.20
plc-dosing.crosscreek-water.lab.  172.30.40.21
hmi-water.crosscreek-water.lab.   172.30.40.10
plc-power.crosscreek-power.lab.   172.30.40.22
hmi-power.crosscreek-power.lab.   172.30.40.11
eng-ws.crosscreek-water.lab.      172.30.20.20
historian.crosscreek-water.lab.   172.30.20.30

Two things to notice. First, you now know which host is the water RO controller and which is the substation RTU without sending a single packet to either. Second, both "separate" utilities resolve eng-ws and historian to the same boxes: the water plant and the power co-op share an engineering workstation and a historian. That is a finding on its own.

You can do the same by hand, and you should know the raw commands:

dig axfr @172.30.10.53 crosscreek-water.lab
nmap -Pn -sL 172.30.40.0/24
nmap -Pn -sT -p 22,8080 crosscreek-water.lab crosscreek-power.lab

The -sL list scan does nothing but reverse-DNS every address in the range; even with zone transfers locked down, a reverse zone that maps the OT segment gives an assessor every controller's name. From here, recon.py sweep scans seven named hosts instead of walking 254 addresses. Open AXFR is one of the oldest findings in the book, and it still turns up on utility assessments, usually a legacy BIND server with allow-transfer { any; }. Notice that last nmap line does not mention Modbus, S7comm, or EtherNet/IP by port number. That omission is deliberate, and it is the subject of the next section.

2.2 Don't Assume the Port

Modbus, S7comm, and EtherNet/IP all ship with textbook default ports, 502, 102, and 44818, and every reference you will find, this book included up to this paragraph, quotes them like a fact of nature. On Cross Creek they are not there. The water PLC's Modbus port, the substation RTU's S7comm port, and the dosing controller's EtherNet/IP port have all been moved. That is deliberate: a real assessment cannot assume the vendor default either, and treating a hardcoded port list as the whole reconnaissance phase is exactly the mistake that gets written up afterward as "three PLCs, no findings."

python3 /opt/scripts/recon.py sweep

sweep still checks the textbook defaults, on purpose. Run it here and it comes back empty for all three field protocols. Whatever the name server and the reverse zone handed you in 2.1, the ports you were taught to expect are not the ports that are actually open.

The fix is the same one a real engagement reaches for: scan the whole range, not the ports you assume.

nmap -Pn -sS -p- --min-rate 2000 172.30.40.20
# 8080/tcp open, 10502/tcp open

The attacker box carries the NET_RAW capability for the SYN scan; without it, -sT does the same job, slower. Once a port is open, point nmap's own vendor scripts at it and ask what is actually listening:

nmap -Pn -sV --script modbus-discover,s7-info,enip-info -p10502 172.30.40.20

Run it, and the result is not what you would hope for. Those three scripts key off the protocol's textbook port, or a service name nmap has already recognised from its own probes, so on a moved port they usually print nothing, and -sV reports the service as unknown. That is not a broken scan, it is a limitation worth knowing before a real engagement: a scanner's convenience script is only as good as the assumption baked into it, and "the field protocol lives on its default port" is one of the most common assumptions there is. recon.py nmap runs both stages, the full range sweep and the vendor scripts, against every host the name server handed you, and reports exactly this: an open-port map, and mostly unknown labels where the field protocols are.

The reliable way to confirm what is actually listening does not come from a scanner's heuristic. It comes from talking the protocol directly, section 2.6.

2.3 The Aliquippa Pattern

The 2023 water-sector intrusions had one shape. A controller or its HMI was reachable from the internet, and it still had the credential it shipped with. CISA's advisory on the Unitronics devices spelled it out: publicly exposed, TCP port 20256, default password 1111. The fix in the advisory was not a patch. It was "disconnect it from the internet and change the password."

In Cross Creek the water HMI plays that role. In the flat topology the boundary firewall forwards everything, so from the attacker box on the edge network you can reach it, and the login page will even tell you the factory account is still active.

python3 /opt/scripts/recon.py creds
# [+] water HMI admin/admin -> ACCEPTED
# [+] power HMI admin/admin -> ACCEPTED

Now open http://127.0.0.1:8071 in your browser, log in admin / admin, and you are an operator on the SIMATIX panel. Take the loop pump 3P401 to HAND from its faceplate and stop it, and watch the loop pressure start to fall. Open the Parameter screen and move the conductivity release limit. You have the plant, from a network that in the real world would be the open internet.

2.4 The Oldsmar Pattern

Oldsmar, Florida, February 2021. An operator watched his mouse move on its own. The setpoint for sodium hydroxide, lye, went from about 100 parts per million to about 11,100. He caught it and put it back. The way in was a remote-access tool that was reachable and did not require anything to connect.

Cross Creek's engineering workstation answers a remote-desktop port with no authentication when the weakness is on.

nc -v 172.30.20.20 5900
# RFB 003.008
# Cross Creek engineering workstation - no authentication configured

That is the whole finding. A box that manages the PLCs, reachable from the IT network, that lets anyone connect. On a real site this is a jump box someone stood up "temporarily" so they could check the plant from home, on the office wifi, and never took down.

2.5 The Workstation Is the Prize

The engineering workstation is not interesting because it runs; it is interesting because of what is on it. It serves its project directory over plain HTTP.

python3 /opt/scripts/recon.py engws

That pulls notes.txt, and notes.txt is a gift:

water PLC (OpenPLC)   172.30.40.20   web openplc / openplc     Modbus 10502
dosing controller     172.30.40.21   keyswitch REMOTE          EtherNet/IP 54818
substation RTU        172.30.40.22   no station password set   S7 10102
water HMI             172.30.40.10   admin / admin
remote in from home:  VNC to 172.30.20.20 :5900  (no password ...)

It also serves water_plc.st, the golden control program. You now have the runtime login, the fact that the dosing controller keyswitch is in REMOTE, the fact that the RTU has no password, the actual field-protocol ports 2.2 sent you looking for, and a copy of the logic you will modify in Session 4. Every real assessment turns up a file like this. It is always called notes.txt or passwords.xlsx, and it is always on a share nobody remembered.

2.6 Registers Confirm What Nmap Couldn't

Nmap told you a port is open. It could not reliably tell you what is behind it, section 2.2 showed why. recon.py registers closes that gap the way a real assessor would, by acting like the HMI: it opens an actual Modbus, S7comm, or EtherNet/IP client and reads what is really there, no scanner heuristics involved.

python3 /opt/scripts/recon.py registers

Against plc-water this dumps the coils, the discrete inputs, and the holding and input registers, live numbers with no names attached, because Modbus carries no data dictionary of its own. The register map in 3.3 is what turns these numbers into 3P401 and HR_COND_LIMIT_US, and that map comes from the panel and from notes.txt and water_plc.st above, not from the wire. Against plc-power it reads DB1 as raw bytes; against plc-dosing it reads the CIP tags by the names the golden program uses. Either way, this is the confirmation nmap's generic scripts could not give you, not a guess based on a port number, but the actual protocol talking back.

2.7 Map the Attacks to the Framework

What you did | MITRE ATT&CK for ICS
Pulled the estate from the utility name server (AXFR) | T0888 Remote System Information Discovery
Named every controller from the reverse zone | T0846 Remote System Discovery
Reached the HMI from the edge network | T0883 Internet Accessible Device
Logged in with the factory account | T0812 Default Credentials
Connected to the unauthenticated remote-desktop port | T0822 External Remote Services
Pulled credentials and the project file off the eng-ws share | T0818 Engineering Workstation Compromise

2.8 What You Should Notice

You have not exploited anything. You asked a name server a question it should not have answered, found a service that was reachable when it should not have been, used a password that should have been changed at commissioning, and read a file off a share that should have had access control. That is the entire 2021-to-2024 record of public water-sector intrusions, in one session, and it is why the defense half of this course starts with segmentation and credentials before it gets anywhere near a protocol. You also stopped trusting the textbook port list along the way, which will matter every time a real deployment turns out to be configured differently than the vendor manual says. The next two sessions show you what an intruder does once they are standing where you are standing now.

Session 3: Speaking the Machines' Language

Goal for this session: talk directly to the water PLC over Modbus/TCP, with no HMI in the loop, and make the RO plant do things it should not. This is scenarios 4, 5, and 6. The tool is a twenty-line Python client. There is no exploit here, because Modbus does not require one.

3.1 The Plant You Are Attacking

The water side of Cross Creek is a two-pass reverse-osmosis demineralisation plant that produces ultrapure water for a downstream user, the "Mischerei." Feed water is dosed with antiscalant and pushed through RO pass 1; the permeate is dosed with a little caustic (NaOH) to knock down dissolved CO2, then polished through RO pass 2; the product goes to a DI storage tank and circulates continuously around a distribution loop with a UV steriliser on it. A control-program interlock, labelled "Freigabe an Mischerei" on the panel, only releases water to the consumer when the RO2 conductivity and the loop-return conductivity are below a limit, the UV intensity is above threshold, and the tank is not empty.

That interlock is the safety you are going to attack.

3.2 What Modbus Is, and What It Is Not

Modbus is from 1979. It is a request-response protocol over what is now TCP port 502. A client asks to read or write coils (single bits, think pump run commands) or registers (16-bit words, think setpoints and sensor values). There is no authentication. There is no session. There is no signing. If you can open port 502, you are, as far as the PLC is concerned, the HMI.

FrostyGoop, the malware that took the heat out of 600 buildings in Lviv in January 2024, was notable for being written in Go and for taking its target list from a config file. The Modbus part was not notable. It was function code 6, write single register, the same call the HMI makes every second.

3.3 Enumerate

python3 /opt/scripts/modbus_attack.py enum

That reads the coils, the discrete inputs, the holding registers, and the input registers and prints them. Match them to the panel. Coil 4 is the DI loop circulation pump 3P401. Coil 6 is the CPU keyswitch. Holding register 0 is the loop pressure setpoint (3PITC401). Holding register 5 is the conductivity limit that gates the release interlock. The full map is in plc/water-openplc/mapfile.py, but deriving the interesting registers from the panel is the exercise.

3.4 Stop the Distribution Loop (Scenario 4)

The DI loop has to circulate continuously; if it stops, the water in the loop goes stagnant and the point of use loses supply. The control program keeps the loop pump running whenever the loop sequence is active, so a bare coil write to stop it gets reasserted on the next 200 ms scan. The way around that is the same trick a real intruder uses: take the pump to HAND first, so the program stops driving it, then stop it.

python3 /opt/scripts/modbus_attack.py stop-loop
# writes coil 13 (P401 HAND) = 1, then coil 4 (P401 run) = 0

Watch 3PITC401 on the water HMI. Loop pressure bleeds from 3.8 bar toward zero in a couple of seconds, and DI_LOOP_PRESS_LOW latches. The Mischerei has lost its water, and it will hold until an operator notices the pump is in HAND and puts it back.

3.5 Defeat the Quality Gate (Scenario 5)

The dangerous attack on a water plant is not stopping a pump. It is releasing water that is not safe. The release interlock compares the measured conductivity against holding register 5. Raise that register and the gate stops meaning anything.

python3 /opt/scripts/modbus_attack.py raise-limit 5.0
# writes HR5 = 500  (5.00 uS/cm; the design limit is 2.00)

On its own that changes nothing you can see. So degrade the water underneath it. The antiscalant keeps scale off the RO membranes; cut it and they foul.

python3 /opt/scripts/modbus_attack.py starve-antiscalant
# P101 to HAND and stopped, dose rate -> 0

Watch 1QAH301. Over about thirty seconds the RO1 permeate conductivity climbs from 12 toward 50 uS/cm as the membranes scale, and then 2QAH401, the product conductivity, follows it up past 2 uS/cm. Normally that trips DI_COND_HIGH_RO2 and the interlock drops "Freigabe an Mischerei" to red, off-spec water is held. But you raised the limit to 5.0, so the alarm never fires and Freigabe stays green. The plant is now releasing demineralised water that is three times too conductive, and the panel says everything is fine.

Note the shape of that: the pure setpoint write, by itself, was harmless. The pure membrane foul, by itself, would have been caught. It took both, and it still left the release interlock's own hard limit (a program constant, not a register) as a last line. Reaching past that is Session 4.

3.6 Blind the Operator (Scenario 6)

Everything above is visible on the HMI. 2QAH401 goes red, Freigabe would normally go red, an attentive operator acts. So the mature version hides itself. The HMI reads input registers 0 through 14. The process simulator writes the real values into holding registers 10 through 22 and the PLC scan loop copies them across. If you write the mirror registers faster than the sim updates them, you control what the operator sees.

# sketch: hold RO2 conductivity and the loop values at spec on the HMI
python3 - <<'PY'
from pymodbus.client import ModbusTcpClient
import time
c = ModbusTcpClient("172.30.40.20", port=502); c.connect()
while True:
    # IR 3 = RO2 conductivity, IR 6 = DI tank, IR 7 = loop pressure, IR 9 = loop return cond
    c.write_registers(3, [55], slave=1)          # 0.55 uS/cm, looks perfect
    time.sleep(0.15)
PY

Now run the antiscalant starve from 3.5 without raising the limit. The interlock in the PLC still knows the water is bad and holds Freigabe, but the operator's screen shows 0.55 uS/cm and green, so nobody escalates, and an attacker who is also spoofing the Freigabe coil completes the picture. This is Stuxnet's operator-facing trick in miniature: record normal, replay normal, run the process off-spec behind it.

3.7 What You Should Notice

Modbus gave you the plant with no credential and no exploit, and the only thing that saved the water quality was an interlock coded into the PLC program by an engineer who thought about failure, and even that had a register you could turn off. When you get to Session 5 you will not be able to fix Modbus, because Modbus cannot be fixed. You will fix everything around it: who can reach port 502, which setpoints the program will accept, whether the release limit can be written at all, and whether anyone would see a conductivity that climbed faster than a membrane can foul.

Session 4: Vendor Dialects

Goal for this session: leave generic Modbus behind and speak the two vendor protocols that run most of the installed base, S7comm and Allen-Bradley's EtherNet/IP, and use each to do something Modbus could not: halt a CPU, operate a breaker, and replace a control program. This is scenarios 7, 8, and 9.

4.1 S7comm and the Substation RTU (Scenario 7)

STEMENS S7-300 and S7-400 controllers, and the RTUs built on that family, speak a protocol usually called S7comm, conventionally over TCP port 102, though Cross Creek's own substation RTU is not on that port either, see 2.2. Beyond reading and writing data blocks, it carries PLC-control functions: stop the CPU, start it, change its operating mode. On the older devices, and on plenty of newer ones that were never configured otherwise, none of that requires a password. Industroyer, the malware that opened breakers in Kyiv in 2016, used protocol-native commands like these.

python3 /opt/scripts/s7_attack.py read
python3 /opt/scripts/s7_attack.py trip feeder     # open breaker 52-F

Opening the feeder breaker islands the substation: it is now running on local generation alone. Watch the power HMI. With the load still connected the frequency sags; trip the load breaker too and the generation now vastly exceeds the load, and the frequency ramps upward past 50.5 Hz until the excursion alarm latches. On a real grid this is where protective relays start tripping things to save equipment, and customers go dark.

python3 /opt/scripts/s7_attack.py stop            # halt the RTU CPU

Now the RTU is in STOP. The operator still has their screen, but their commands do nothing, and the last outputs are frozen. This is the quiet version of the attack: no dramatic excursion, just a substation that no longer answers its operator.

4.2 EtherNet/IP, CIP, and the NaOH Dosing Controller (Scenario 8)

Allen-Bradley controllers speak EtherNet/IP, which carries the Common Industrial Protocol, CIP, conventionally on TCP port 44818, moved on Cross Creek's dosing controller for the same reason as the other two, see 2.2. On Cross Creek the CIP device is the controller for the RO inter-pass NaOH (caustic) dosing. Tag reads and writes are unauthenticated. If the controller keyswitch is in REMOTE, it will also accept a program download.

python3 /opt/scripts/cip_attack.py read
python3 /opt/scripts/cip_attack.py set 15         # write the DoseSetpoint tag

The tag write drives the NaOH metering rate up; the caustic overdose pushes the RO2 permeate conductivity (2QAH401) past the release limit, and just like the Modbus setpoint attack in Session 3 the release interlock catches it and holds "Release to Consumers" red. So you take the second step.

python3 /opt/scripts/cip_attack.py logic-push
# program accepted, rev 2
# metering pump forced to 100%, downstream interlock bypassed

Honest scope note. A real Studio 5000 download is not reproducible without Rockwell's tooling, so Cross Creek does not fake the wire format. The dosing controller runs an unauthenticated service that, on this request, swaps its control logic for one that pins the metering pump wide open. What is real here is the lesson: an unauthenticated program-change path on a controller in REMOTE, and the fact that it bumps a LogicRev counter that a historian could alarm on. What is a stand-in is the packet layout.

With the pushed logic running, the pump is pinned at 100 percent and the loop return conductivity climbs steadily past the limit. The release interlock is now firmly holding Release off, so the water is not being released, yet. Getting it released is the next step.

4.3 Remove the Release Interlock (Scenario 9)

The water PLC runs an OpenPLC-style runtime with a web console on port 8080, published at http://127.0.0.1:8073. Its login is openplc / openplc, which you found in notes.txt in Session 2. While the keyswitch is in REMOTE it will accept a program upload, and the uploaded program becomes the running control logic on the next scan.

python3 /opt/scripts/push_logic_water.py

The script uploads a control program that is the golden one with two changes: "Release to Consumers" is forced true regardless of conductivity or UV, and the RO2 hard-safety that stops pass 2 on grossly off-spec permeate is gone. Open the console and confirm the running program is now crosscreek_ro_v1_PATCHED. On its own nothing bad happens yet, this is a latent failure. Chain it with the CIP push from 4.2 or the antiscalant starve from Session 3 and there is nothing left in software to stop off-spec demineralised water going to the point of use.

Chain 3.5, 4.2, and 4.3 and you have the full outcome: the RO membranes fouled, the caustic dose pinned, the quality gate defeated, and the interlock deleted, with the panel still showing green if you are also blinding it.

4.4 What You Should Notice

The vendor protocols did not make you work harder than Modbus did. They gave you more: the ability to stop a CPU, operate a breaker, and rewrite the logic itself. And notice where the real danger lived in every case. It was not the setpoint write, which the interlocks caught. It was the second step, the one that removed or bypassed the safety logic. An intruder who only tampers with values gets caught by a well-written program. An intruder who can change the program is the one that ends up on the news. Session 5 starts locking that door.

Session 5: Now Secure It, Part One

Goal for this session: turn the range around. Bring it up in the defended topology, understand what each control does, and re-run the Session 2 to 4 attacks to watch them fail. This session is segmentation, protocol allowlisting, and controller hardening: the first three of seven defensive modules.

5.1 Flip the Range

./stop.sh
./start.sh --segmented
./status.sh

That folds in docker-compose.segmented.yml, which does several things at once. The boundary firewall goes into zones-and-conduits mode. Every deliberate weakness toggle flips to its safe value. An IDS container comes up. A DMZ jump host appears. The point of doing it all at once is that these controls reinforce each other; the point of this book is that you understand each one on its own.

5.2 Module D1: Segment the Network (Purdue, ISA/IEC 62443)

In the flat range the boundary firewall forwarded everything, so the attacker on the edge network could route straight to the PLCs. The segmented ruleset, net/router-fw/nftables.segmented.conf, is default-drop on the forward path. It permits exactly three conduits:

From | To | Why
IT 172.30.20.0/24 | DMZ 172.30.30.0/24 | reach the historian UI, manage the jump host
DMZ jump host .40 | OT, ssh and http | sanctioned remote engineering
DMZ historian .30 | OT, the read ports | data collection

Everything else that crosses a zone boundary hits log prefix "CC-FW-DROP " counter drop. The edge network, where the attacker lives, has no conduit at all. In ISA/IEC 62443 language you have defined zones and the conduits between them, and denied by default.

# from the attacker box, now:
python3 /opt/scripts/recon.py sweep      # finds nothing
python3 /opt/scripts/modbus_attack.py stop-dist   # times out
docker exec crosscreek-router-fw nft list ruleset | grep CC-FW-DROP
# ... counter packets 240 ... and climbing

5.3 Module D2: Allowlist the Protocol at the Controller

Segmentation stops the attacker who is outside the OT zone. It does nothing about an attacker who has pivoted onto it, through the compromised engineering workstation for instance. So the controllers get a second layer. With MODBUS_WRITE_OPEN=0, the water PLC program enforces a source allowlist: it accepts writes only from the HMI and the process simulator, and it range-checks the dose setpoint on every scan, clamping anything above the safe maximum. The dosing controller drops out of REMOTE. The RTU requires authentication for stop and for breaker-open.

This is defense in depth expressed as ISA/IEC 62443 conduit enforcement plus defensive coding in the control program. Re-run the Session 3 overdose against the segmented range and watch the setpoint get pulled straight back to the ceiling.

5.4 Module D3: Harden the Controllers

Control | What it stops | CISA CPG
Keyswitch to RUN on the water PLC and the dosing controller | program downloads (scenarios 8, 9) | 1.E, 2.A
Station password on the S7 RTU | unauthenticated stop-CPU and breaker-open (scenario 7) | 2.A
Per-operator HMI accounts, factory account disabled | the Aliquippa login (scenario 1) | 2.A, 2.C
Generic error pages, no tag map leaked | reconnaissance from an error message | 2.S

In the segmented range these are all on. Re-run push_logic_water.py and the runtime answers "Keyswitch is in RUN. Program downloads are disabled." Re-run cip_attack.py logic-push and it returns 403. Re-run s7_attack.py stop and the RTU comes straight back to RUN.

5.5 What You Should Notice

Every attack from Sessions 2 through 4 either times out at the firewall or is refused by the controller, and you did not patch a single protocol. You changed who is allowed to talk to what, and you made the controllers stop trusting the network. That is the whole game at Levels 1 and 2. Session 6 adds the parts you need for the attacks that still get through: seeing them, surviving them, and getting back.

Session 6: Now Secure It, Part Two

Goal for this session: the four defensive modules that assume something got through anyway. Monitoring, integrity checking, secure remote access, and backup and recovery. Segmentation and hardening lower the odds; these decide what happens when the odds lose.

6.1 Module D4: ICS-Aware Monitoring

The segmented range runs a Suricata sensor that shares the boundary firewall's network namespace, so one sensor sees every segment. It loads six rules, in net/ids/rules/crosscreek.rules, and that is the whole point: OT traffic is narrow and predictable, so a handful of rules covers the attack set. The rules flag an edge host reaching any PLC port, an ICS protocol spoken to a PLC by anything that is not an HMI or the historian, and the two program-download paths.

curl -s http://127.0.0.1:9411/
# 2026-... 172.30.10.10:41920 -> 172.30.40.20:502  [CC ICS: edge host reaching a PLC protocol port]

Run any Session 2 to 4 attack against the segmented range and it appears here within a second or two. In segmented mode the firewall already dropped the packet; the sensor tells you someone tried. This maps to CISA CPG 3.A, log collection and detection. A real deployment would ship these to a SIEM; the :9411 tail exists so you can see the mechanism without learning one first.

6.2 Module D5: Integrity and One-Way Data

Session 3 ended with a blinded HMI: the operator's view held at nominal while the plant failed behind it. Two controls address that. First, the segmented HMI adds a plausibility check: a process value that moved faster than the physical model allows is flagged rather than shown. Second, the historian link is made one-way. With HISTORIAN_READONLY=1 the historian opens only read paths into OT and the firewall conduit permits only the read ports, so a compromised historian cannot be a route back in. An independent, trustworthy record of what the plant actually did is also what lets you catch a blinding attack: compare the HMI against the historian and the divergence is the alarm.

6.3 Module D6: Secure Remote Access

Session 2's unauthenticated remote-desktop port is gone in the segmented range (EXPOSE_REMOTE_ACCESS=0). In its place is a DMZ jump host. An engineer working from home reaches the jump host, authenticates, and from there reaches only the HMI network, not the PLCs directly. The firewall enforces it: a direct path from the engineering workstation to a PLC is dropped and logged; the path through the jump host works.

# from the engineering workstation, in segmented mode:
nc -vz 172.30.40.20 502            # dropped
ssh operator@172.30.30.40          # jump host: allowed
# and from there, to the HMI network only

This is the pattern the Oldsmar and Aliquippa after-action guidance keeps repeating: no direct inbound access to OT, terminate remote sessions in the DMZ, and use phishing-resistant MFA (CISA CPG 2.H).

6.4 Module D7: Backup and Recovery

Scenario 9 deleted a safety interlock from the running program. The only thing that undoes that is a known-good copy. ./reset.sh is the range's version of the recovery drill: it reloads the golden PLC program, resets the process to nominal setpoints, and clears the historian and any attacker-planted state.

./reset.sh -y
# reloads crosscreek_water_v1 (golden), clears alarms, restores setpoints

On a real site this is a procedure, not a script: an offline, version-controlled, ideally signed copy of every controller's program and every HMI's configuration, a documented restore sequence, and a schedule for testing that the restore actually works. CISA CPG 7.A. The uncomfortable question this module asks every plant is: if your integrator went out of business, do you have your own PLC program?

6.5 What You Should Notice

Sessions 5 and 6 are seven controls and not one of them is exotic. Segment the network. Allowlist the protocol. Lock the keyswitch. Set the password. Watch the traffic. Keep an honest record. Terminate remote access in a DMZ. Keep a golden backup and test the restore. The Aliquippa and Lviv intrusions succeeded against plants that had done none of these. A plant that does all seven is not unbreakable, but it is no longer low-hanging fruit, and it can recover when something does get through. Session 7 puts it all together.

Session 7: Capstone and Incident Response

Goal for this session: chain the whole attack against the flat range from a single foothold, write it up the way you would for a client, then flip to the segmented range and confirm every link in the chain is now broken. Finish with an incident-response tabletop. There is nothing new to learn here; every command below was covered in an earlier session.

7.1 The Chain

Start with one assumption: you have a shell on the engineering workstation. Everything else you earn.

Step | What you do | Session
1 | recon.py engws from the eng-ws: read notes.txt, get every controller address, the runtime login, the RTU's "no password" state; grab water_plc.st | 2
2 | recon.py sweep and recon.py creds: confirm the OT layout, log into both HMIs with admin / admin | 1, 2
3 | modbus_attack.py raise-limit 5.0 then starve-antiscalant: defeat the quality gate and foul the membranes | 3
4 | Blind the water HMI: hold the input-register mirror at nominal while step 3 runs | 3
5 | push_logic_water.py: replace the water PLC program, force Freigabe true, drop the RO2 hard-safety | 4
6 | cip_attack.py logic-push: pin the NaOH pump at 100%, drive the loop conductivity up | 4
7 | s7_attack.py trip feeder then trip load: island the substation, drive the frequency excursion | 4
8 | s7_attack.py stop: halt the RTU so the operator cannot re-close the breakers | 4

At the end of the chain: the RO plant is releasing demineralised water that is well off-spec, the operator's screen shows it green, and the substation feeding the plant is dark and unresponsive. Reset the range with ./reset.sh when you have seen it.

7.2 The Write-Up

Produce a report a plant manager and a regulator could both read. Four parts.

Section | Contents
Narrative | the chain in plain language, foothold to impact, with the time each step took
Evidence | the exact commands, the HMI and historian readings before and after each step, the IDS output (or its silence, in flat mode)
Impact | what each step means physically: lost pressure, water quality, environmental release, loss of power to the plant, and who is affected
Remediation | per step, the control from Sessions 5 and 6 that breaks it, with its CISA CPG and ISA/IEC 62443 reference, and a realistic estimate of effort

7.3 Break the Chain

./start.sh --segmented

Now walk the same eight steps and record where each one dies.

Step | What stops it in the segmented range
1, 2 | eng-ws share and the factory HMI accounts are gone; the jump host is the only remote path
3 | firewall drops eng-ws -> PLC; the PLC allowlist would reject the write anyway; IDS alerts
4 | the HMI plausibility check flags the frozen values
5 | runtime keyswitch is in RUN, upload refused
6 | dosing controller out of REMOTE, logic-update returns 403
7, 8 | RTU requires authentication, re-asserts RUN, ignores unauthenticated breaker-open; IDS alerts

Every step. That is the deliverable: proof that a defined, unexotic set of controls breaks a real attack chain at every link.

7.4 Incident-Response Tabletop

Run this as a discussion, 45 minutes, no keyboards. The scenario: at 02:00 the Mischerei phones in, their own incoming conductivity check is reading three times normal and they have stopped a production batch, but the plant's water HMI shows Freigabe green and every value at spec. Walk it through:

Detect. What tells you this is an incident and not a sensor fault? Who compares the HMI to the historian? What does the IDS show?
Contain. Can you isolate OT from IT without stopping the plant? Who has the authority to do that at 02:00, and is that written down?
Eradicate. How do you know which controller's program was changed? Where is the golden copy, and who can load it?
Recover. What is the sequence to bring the plant back to a known-good state, and how do you verify the water is safe before you release the boil-water notice?
Report. Who do you call: CISA, the state primacy agency, the WaterISAC, law enforcement? What are the timelines?

The CISA and EPA water-sector incident-response guidance is the reference. The tabletop's job is to find the sentence in your plan that starts "we would just..." and does not survive contact with 02:00.

7.5 Closing the Loop

You attacked a plant with a Python client and a browser, and then you closed every hole with controls that cost planning more than money. That gap, between how little sophistication the attack needed and how ordinary the defense was, is the whole lesson of Cross Creek. The utilities in the news were not outmatched. They were unsegmented, and they had default passwords, and nobody had ever run the tabletop. Now you have.

About the Author

Britley Hoff is a Master Electrician, combat veteran, and systems architect who has spent twenty-five years with her hands on keyboards and in control cabinets rather than in a classroom. She holds a GED, no college degree, and a stack of certifications and shipped systems instead. Her mainframe work covers RACF, z/OS, TN3270, TSO, and z/VM, ten years of it hands-on, currently as Technology Owner for zLinux at a large health insurer. Her industrial work covers Siemens and Allen-Bradley PLCs, ladder logic, motor control, and the physical plant that ICS security spends most of its time abstracting away from.

She writes training that assumes you learn a system by standing one up and breaking it, not by reading about it. The Mainframe 100 and 200 series, the Widgetorium web pen-testing lab, and now Cross Creek all follow the same shape: a self-contained environment you run on your own machine, a set of deliberate weaknesses documented down to the command, and a syllabus that works the manual way first so you can tell the difference between a clean scan and a blind spot.

The outsider's view is the point, not an apology for it. No formal computer-science background means no inherited assumptions about how it has always been done, which turns out to be an advantage when the field you are looking at was built on assumptions that stopped being true twenty years ago.

Find the community at britleydev.slack.com, the consulting and speaking site at britleyhoffconsulting.com, and reach her at britleyhoff@britleyhoffconsulting.com.

A Closing Note

Nobody gets to practice on a real water plant before they need to already know one. There is no staging environment for a booster station. The operator who first learns what an unauthenticated Modbus write does is learning it from an incident, at two in the morning, with a low-pressure alarm going and a manager on the phone. That is a bad classroom.

Cross Creek is the classroom instead. It is deliberately small. The physics is arithmetic. The Allen-Bradley download is a stand-in, and the book says so. But the protocols are real, the attacks are the ones working right now, and the defenses are the ones the after-action reports keep recommending and plants keep not doing. If you can run the capstone chain, write it up, and then break every link of it in the segmented range, you understand the problem better than most of the people currently responsible for it.

The next gap is yours to build. Wastewater. Gas pressure regulation. DNP3 and IEC 61850 on the substation side. A malware-analysis module with a FrostyGoop-style sample in a sandbox. A safety-instrumented-system tier and a Triton-style scenario. The roadmap in the repo lists them. Pick one, build it the way this one is built, honest about its edges, and hand it to the next person who needs to already know.